<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://axelparmentier.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://axelparmentier.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-13T15:19:18+00:00</updated><id>https://axelparmentier.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Axel Parmentier academic page </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The joy of being an applied mathematician</title><link href="https://axelparmentier.github.io/blog/2024/AppliedMathPriviledges/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The joy of being an applied mathematician"/><published>2024-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://axelparmentier.github.io/blog/2024/AppliedMathPriviledges</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://axelparmentier.github.io/blog/2024/AppliedMathPriviledges/"><![CDATA[<p>Fifteen years ago, in the rigorous setting of a preparatory class <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, a friend challenged my perception of our studies. He argued that the mathematics we were delving into did not encompass his intellectual and spiritual <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> life. At the time, I disagreed, yet I found myself unable to articulate the connection I sensed between our mathematical endeavors and the broader intellectual realms.</p> <p>Today, as a professional applied mathematician, I have found the words that eluded me then. Mathematics, I have come to realize, is not just a tool for solving problems but a gateway to understanding other fields of knowledge. It is a source of joy that goes beyond the boundaries of professional work.</p> <p>This post is not a boastful declaration but an exploration of the satisfaction one can experience in the profession of mathematics. It is a description of the perks that come with being a mathematician. While describing what I enjoy in the job, I am aware of the potential for confirmation bias justifying my career choice. Yet, this self-awareness does not diminish the joy I find in my work.</p> <h2 id="mathematics-as-the-language-of-science">Mathematics as the language of science</h2> <p>In the realm of intellectual pursuits, applied mathematicians enjoy a perk that stems from their fluency in mathematics. Mathematics is not a science but the language of science and technology. It is this foundational role that bestows upon mathematicians a remarkable ability to delve into virtually any scientific theory or technical discipline <sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. Indeed, when we discuss with a scientist from another field, say for instance a biologist, we can manage to understand the problem they work on because we can understand the underlying mathematics of their models.</p> <p>In that, we perhaps inherit a small part of the universal thinkers of yesterday, who mastered disciplines from science to philosophy. Today, philosophy struggles to grasp the intricacies of science and technology, which are the driving forces behind the changes and transformations shaping our world. In contrast, mathematicians, should they exert the effort, are capable of understanding not only the sciences and technologies but also the writings of philosophers if they so desire. Well, perhaps not Heidegger. For the applied mathematician, life is not just a series of equations to be solved but a tapestry of knowledge to be woven into a comprehensive understanding of the universe we inhabit.</p> <h2 id="applied-mathematicians-modeling-the-world">Applied Mathematicians: Modeling the World</h2> <p>One of the key distinctions in the field of mathematics is between pure mathematicians and applied mathematicians. While pure mathematicians are driven by the intrinsic beauty and complexity of mathematics itself, applied mathematicians harness mathematical tools not to study mathematics for its own sake, but to model the world around us. This modeling approach is arguably the most advanced technique in human endeavors, allowing for a logical and effective understanding of the world, and the ability to construct tangible outcomes based on this understanding <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.</p> <p>Applied mathematicians are, therefore, not just scholars of abstract concepts; they are the architects of models that mirror reality. Their work translates into the design of systems, the optimization of processes, and the prediction of outcomes, which are essential in various industries and sectors. A perk of being an applied mathematician lies in the ability to apply theoretical knowledge to practical problems, bridging the gap between the world of ideas and the world of human experience.</p> <h2 id="operational-research-and-economic-applications">Operational Research and economic applications</h2> <p>Operational research focuses modeling and optimizing economical and industrial processes. <a href="/blog/2024/ORmodern/">It applies the tools of applied mathematics to decode the economic world, and address socio-economic and ecological challenges</a>. Contrarily to economists, we do not want to debate on what should be the rules. Operational researchers use mathematical rigor to develop algorithms that take the best possible decisions effectively on a large scale given these rules. These algorithms are designed to capture the full complexity of real-world scenarios, providing more accurate and actionable insights.</p> <p>Therefore, the field of operational research exposes practitioners to a wide array of industrial sectors, offering a rich tapestry of professional interests and opportunities. This breadth of exposure allows operational researchers to discover and appreciate the nuances of numerous professions.</p> <h2 id="individual-simplicity-amidst-collective-wealth">Individual simplicity amidst collective wealth</h2> <p>I would like to conclude this post by a humorous tribute to the Jesuits schools where I had the chance to study. One of the general culture teacher, who was not a Jesuit but a conservative French intellectual, had the habit to say: “Jesuits understand everything to how to live a comfortable intellectual life. Indeed, they live a life of individual simplicity amidst collective wealth, enjoying the privileges of money without its burdens, nor the burdens of family”. François Varillon, a French Jesuit of the twentieth century, wrote one of the greatest satisfactions of Jesuit life is the intellectual friendships that are forged over decades.<br/> Like the Jesuits, academics live a life of individual simplicity amidst a collective wealth of knowledge. We forge intellectual bonds, built upon shared curiosity and the pursuit of knowledge, which are the unseen treasures of our academic profession. Unlike the Jesuits, however, we also have the opportunity to enjoy family life. In the dance of family life, the rhythm of joy outsteps the small steps of daily duties.</p> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p><strong>Understanding the French ‘Classe Préparatoire’:</strong> In France, a ‘classe préparatoire’, often abbreviated as ‘prépa’, is a highly intensive and prestigious program that prepares high school graduates for entrance exams to ‘Grandes Écoles’. These are elite higher education institutions outside the mainstream framework of the public universities system. Classes préparatoires are known for their rigorous curriculum, which typically spans two years and covers advanced topics in science, humanities, or commerce. Students in these programs often undergo a demanding schedule with long hours of coursework, aiming to excel in competitive exams that grant access to schools in engineering, business, or other specialized fields. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2"> <p><strong>No mysticism, please !</strong> I would like to dispel three potential misunderstandings that could arise from my reflections. First, it is not my intention to present mathematics as a form of mysticism. Every math teacher has encountered among their students those who are zealots and mystics of mathematics, who tend not to be the best mathematicians. What I meant by spiritual is that we recognize an aesthetic in mathematical theories akin to the admiration one might feel for the beauty of art. And certainly not any kind of mystical belief. Secondly, it would be a mistake to believe that mathematics replaces religion. Even though I consider mathematics to be the most advanced form of human knowledge, it does not supplant others areas of knowledge when it comes to describing human experience. Mathematics is a powerful tool for understanding the world, but it does not claim to provide a comprehensive view of our experience of reality, nor does it fulfill the role that spiritual beliefs play in individuals’ lives. As Harvard’s theologian Harvey Cox points out in the introduction of <em>the future of faith</em>, there is joy in recognizing that previous generations faced the same questions about life’s mysteries – questions to which mathematics cannot provide answers. However, just as one can experience a sense of wonder at religious beauty, one can also feel awe at the beauty of ideas, and even more at the beauty of the world, a feeling that is enhanced by practicing mathematics and gaining a better understanding. The more we delve into mathematics, the more we understand it, and through its tools, the more we perceive the world. Yet, this deepening understanding also brings a profound realization of how little we actually know about the world and mathematics itself. It highlights the vast expanse of knowledge yet to be discovered and allows us to appreciate the beauty of these ideas and the world even more. This experience of beauty may be the scientists’ version of experiencing the transcendence ‘toward-which’ man tends discussed by theologians like Karl Rahner. Finally, mathematics should not be confused with religious practice. Harvard’s theologian Harvey Cox, in his book “The Market as God,” highlights how some economists treat their discipline as a theology. Thankfully, mathematicians do not fall into this trap. We do not claim to hold absolute truths as theologians might, nor to whisper in the ears of politicians, but rather work collectively to develop theories based on logic and reason. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4"> <p>I definitely do not mean that mathematicians can talk as experts on matters of other fields. We unfortunately heard during COVID too many established scientists pretending to give a scientific opinion on something they are not expert of. This goes against scientific ethic. I just mean that we can understand enough of other sciences to take pleasure in this discovery, and sometimes to collaborate with experts of the field. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>This perk is also enjoyed by Physicists, and other practitioners of hard mathematized sciences <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion"/><category term="Applied"/><category term="Mathematics,"/><category term="Operations"/><category term="Research,"/><category term="Philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[About the perks that come with being an applied mathematician.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Operations Research, a modern perspective</title><link href="https://axelparmentier.github.io/blog/2024/ORmodern/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Operations Research, a modern perspective"/><published>2024-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://axelparmentier.github.io/blog/2024/ORmodern</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://axelparmentier.github.io/blog/2024/ORmodern/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is written for non-experts, and more precisely industrialists who want to know more about operations research and for young colleagues who contemplate starting a career in the field. I give my current opinion on why operations research matters, how it brings value to society. I conclude with the main scientific challenges.</em></p> <h2 id="why-operations-research">Why Operations Research</h2> <p>The ecological transition may be the greatest challenge of our generation. The latest IPCC report emphasizes the need to act on two fronts simultaneously to curb global warming: adopting a more frugal lifestyle and improving our production methods. The latter is painless for the end consumer, as it involves producing the same goods and services more efficiently. As long as they are economically feasible, environmentally-focused policies based on technology are thus more widely accepted. It is important to implement them as effectively as possible.</p> <p>When discussing environmental technologies, public debate often centers on renewable energy or low-carbon transportation. However, better decisions can also be made with existing technology. Take home delivery, for example. Investing in electric vehicles can reduce emissions. Better organization of delivery routes can also decrease the distance traveled to make the same deliveries, thereby reducing emissions as well. Yet, manually constructing efficient vehicle routes is challenging. Even with the best techniques, manually created solutions result in routes that are, on average, 13% longer than the optimal solution. To improve this, decision-support algorithms are needed. These algorithms can reduce emissions and costs by optimizing the use of available resources. They represent the mathematical and industrial version of waste reduction.</p> <p>Operations research is the mathematical discipline that provides such decision-support tools. A typical outcome of an operations research project in industry is the ability to produce more cost-effectively and with fewer resources, without changing production means or technology. Advances in the field and greater data accessibility have increased the potential applications of operations research. These methods are currently underutilized outside of network industries and represent a significant source of economic and environmental value.</p> <h2 id="main-drivers-of-performance-in-operations-research">Main drivers of performance in Operations Research</h2> <p>In Operations Research, the most critical factor for success is <strong>modeling</strong>. This involves translating the optimization of an industrial process into a mathematical problem. The most sophisticated algorithms are futile if they don’t address the correct problem. But this reality takes a particular flavor in Operations Research. Manual optimization of industrial processes is arduous. Over time, companies have developed numerous heuristics to streamline these processes, such as “visit each client every two days” or “truck routes should not serve more than three clients.” Initially, these rules were adopted to simplify the planner’s task, not out of industrial necessity, and over time they have become sacrosanct. However, with the advent of computing power and sophisticated algorithms for optimizing industrial processes, these rules can become obsolete and even detrimental. They restrict optimization, leading to reduced performance. Essentially, <em>altering the rules of the game often yields greater benefits than improving gameplay within the existing framework</em>.</p> <p>Beyond modeling, the next pivotal element for enhancing performance is <strong>combinatorial optimization</strong>. Specifically, the development of combinatorial optimization algorithms that are scalable. Optimization, a branch of applied mathematics, is dedicated to minimizing functions. In essence, it seeks the optimal solutions that meet a specific goal while adhering to certain constraints. In the context of industrial processes, optimization typically involves the allocation of resources like vehicles and machinery. These resources are often non-splittable, leading to binary or integer variables. For example, a plane either operates a flight or it doesn’t; there’s no such thing as half a plane on a flight. Combinatorial optimization deals with these integer variables. When it comes to industrial processes, <em>performance is largely driven by economies of scale</em>. For instance, a company delivering parcels in a city will face inefficiencies if only a few clients are spread out. However, with a higher number of clients, particularly in the same area, the delivery process becomes more efficient, allowing for reduced marginal costs. Thus, after a process is modeled, the primary profit lever is the reduction of marginal costs. Achieving these economies of scale necessitates algorithms that can take a holistic view of the process—algorithms that perform well even as the scale of operations grows. Creating combinatorial algorithms that can handle large-scale applications is a significant mathematical challenge, both theoretically and practically. This complexity is why <em>operations research scholars have concentrated on combinatorial optimization for the past seven decades</em>.</p> <p>Finally, the last driver of performance is <strong>data</strong>. As the saying goes <em>garbage in, garbage out</em>. Data on industrial processes used to be scarce. Two decades of digitalization of industrial processes have changed the game. However, if data is now abundant, it is sometimes incomplete and often inherently random, which makes <strong>machine learning</strong> the suitable discipline for managing uncertainty in their analysis and processing.</p> <p>When it comes to the tangible benefits of optimizing industrial processes, the hierarchy of impact generally begins with modeling, followed by combinatorial optimization, and finally, machine learning. Applied mathematics and computer science scholars who work on Operations Research tend to focus on the methodological aspects, which lie on the optimization and on the learning side. Modeling is more an art than a scientific discipline. While a comprehensive understanding of mathematical tools is essential, it’s not the sole requirement for proficiency. True expertise in modeling also demands an appreciation for economic significance and a well-honed ability to engage with industry professionals. This engagement is crucial for speaking their language, and being able to challenge the rules of the games to unlock value. </p> <h2 id="todays-top-challenges-in-operations-research">Today’s Top Challenges in Operations Research</h2> <p>Two elements have profoundly changed the operations research landscape during the last decades. First process digitalization have made data abundant and algorithm much easier to integrate in workflows. Second, dramatic progress have been made on combinatorial optimization. Indeed, given the hierarchy of benefits previously outlined, it comes as no surprise that the operations research community has focused on building algorithms that scales, even if this means simplifying the objective. And it has been widely successful in this endeavor. Consider for instance mixed integer linear programming (MILP), which could be described as the Swiss knife of combinatorial optimization. On the same computer, the 2015 version of a well-known solver is 780 thousands times faster than the 1991 version. If we factor the hardware improvements, we get a 450 billion times speed-up. Problems with millions of variables and constraints are now routinely solved in the industry. As a result, <em>efficient off the shelf algorithms are now available</em> for static and deterministic Operations Research problems. <strong>Operations research is therefore now widely applicable in the industry, and still underused</strong>. One brake to the adoption is that these algorithms require appropriate modeling for being efficient. For instance, many MILP formulations can model the same problem, some efficiently solved by MILP solvers, some not. Hence, there are many low-hanging fruits, i.e., industrial processes that can be optimized over three months projects. But grabbing them may require an expert at the early modeling stage.</p> <p>While operations research tools were getting more and more efficient, industrial needs have been evolving. First, the COVID era has underlined the need for <em>resilience</em> especially in supply chain. From a scientific perspective, this requires handling risks coming from random events that may affect the process. Practically, information on this randomness is available in the now abundant data on industrial processes. Statistical challenge must be address to exploit these data to manage the risks inherent to industrial processes. Second, the <em>ecological transition</em> introduce several additional challenges. First, they introduce new combinatorial optimization challenge. For instance, operating a multimodal supply chain requires synchronizing trains arrival and truck departures. Second, they introduce additional randomness, such as the uncertainty on sun and wind power. This reinforces the need to exploit data to manage uncertainty when optimizing processes.</p> <p>Hence, we believe that the main scientific challenge for operations research is to develop a new generation of <strong>scalable and data driven optimization algorithms that make industrial processes more efficient and resilient</strong>. While <em>combinatorial optimization</em> is the appropriate scientific discipline to address the scalability aspects, <em>machine learning</em> is the appropriate one to handle the data driven aspect. And a series of scientific work have shown that these combinatorial and statistical aspects must be dealt with simultaneously, as we otherwise end-up with a statistically intractable machine learning problem followed by a computationally intractable optimization problem.</p> <h2 id="my-methodological-research">My methodological research</h2> <p>Following the diagnostics above, most of my methodological research is focused on developing algorithms that merge machine learning and combinatorial optimization tools to handle data driven problem. This has pushed me to work on <em>contextual stochastic optimization</em>: Given a context that contains all the information available on a process, how to take the best decision. Practically, this requires building a policy that maps a context to a decision. To build such a policy, I chain a neural network, which handles the statistical aspects, with a combinatorial optimization algorithm. The neural network therefore outputs the parameters of a combinatorial optimization algorithm, and the combinatorial algorithm outputs the decision. Two scientific challenges must be addressed and are the focus of my research. First, adequate architectures must be identified for the neural network and the combinatorial optimization. Second, such an approach can be efficient only if we develop efficient algorithms to learn from data the right parametrization of the neural network. Efficient algorithms must train the neural network in an integrated way, i.e., by minimizing the error on the decisions and not on the parameters.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion"/><category term="OR"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An opinionated perspective on the field of Operations Research]]></summary></entry></feed>